e
[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome back to the ask abijit show
hope everybody is doing
great okay before we begin with the
questions let me see who all is on the
live stream I can see Rashmi prakar
Gupta chat DSP rudra Dr Atul Tushar
kalburgi Richard Savage rash yashan
Singh Chan rajil Kare agba mukad
Narendra om prash prash seven truth I
blame harsh ban J manraj Singh Surendra
Gupta Kushi Sharma Brahma jadav parij
diit bageshwar Army Rio mugan anupam
jwal Sanda f Arian takur Mr manik
Krishna ginda Alfred ragunath from the
Surinam Netherlands geopolitical
Dubai Anand sutum bianda Panda Aman J
Singh Vishnu mohanan feminist Slayer YK
ragir solanki DJ kamat animish aru and
aan Rio mugan Rahul dun Alvin
Rodriguez who all do we have who else do
we have I blame har animish Dr Atul
Rashmi okay we got those people snea
Surendra Gupta adya Kumar vardi 13
tanmoy chakrabarti pankaj tanay putan
Vishnu Gopi Ajay Kanani nikil guitar
Aris mansen PM David Savage and
everybody else okay I'm going to stop uh
greeting you all as always uh so in the
past few live streams some people have
said rightfully that uh in live stream
sometimes questions get repeated
and certain questions aren't up to the
high quality standards that we expect
because well you can't expect everything
may expect me to be able to get the best
questions while while answering
questions on a live stream so because of
that I have decided to take some
questions from the comments the
questions that you've asked in the
comments and the others I will take from
the live chat so it's going to be a
hybrid session some questions I'll take
from the from the comments and some
questions the rest I will take uh from
the live chat that you are asking me
right now so let me Begin by taking one
question from the comments and this is
by Rajiv Agarwal
7047 and it's a request if possible
please put short videos of every every
question that I answer like I do with
some questions okay so it's there but I
suppose no one is aware of this so let
me put that on the screen I have a
separate Channel called the Abhijit
Chava Clips channel on which you will
see that I I put up all these clips of
the questions that I answer so it's all
here uh typically if I do a live stream
today within 5 six days all the
questions will the questions will be
I'll start to put them up over here so I
put about six seven questions a day on
this channel and you will get uh all the
clips of the questions I've have
answered on this channel so it's the
abijit Chava Clips Channel I have uh
pinned that in the live chat so if
you're interested if you if you don't
have the time to watch the entire live
stream then you can go and check out the
channel you can subscribe to subscribe
to it if you if you wish and uh the link
to the channel is in the description at
the bottom and it's also pinned in the
live chat so check it out so that that
that solves this problem for those of
you who don't have the time to uh watch
an entire live stream right okay let's
take some questions uh from the uh from
the chat live chat
uh manand says what is India's biggest
soft power right now and how is the of
power changed over the years so uh yeah
there are two kinds two main kinds of
power right hard power and soft power so
let's first understand what's hard power
very briefly hard power is your economic
power and military power that's
essentially what it is the combination
of those two things and there are other
factors also like your geographical area
your population your power projection
ability how Sovereign you are how energy
independent you are all of that but
mainly it's your economic strength plus
your military might that's hard power
now what is soft power soft power
is power that you use to get things done
without compelling someone so in case so
it's it's about soft power is all about
persuasion it's all about your
reputation it's it's whether you are
admired or not internationally you as in
your nation right so nations
with high soft power
are nations that are culturally very
relevant Nations that are admired
worldwide for various things etc for
example Korea is known for K-pop and
there are millions and billions of not
billions but hundreds of millions of
fans of K-pop worldwide including young
girls in India apparently I'm not aware
but so that gives Korea a great
reputation and these people who admire
K-pop and who are fans of kok will want
to visit Korea and they will hold Korea
in high in a high in high regard
similarly this Japanese manga anemy all
of that Japan overall is a highly
technologically advanced nation very
beautiful Nation so that uh makes it
rise in the estimation of a lot of
people worldwide so that is Japan soft
power when it comes to the US it's it's
the number one nation in hard power but
even when it comes to soft power
elements like Hollywood it it uh it's a
great persuasive tool it's a great
propaganda machine Hollywood isn't it
then the US military industry sorry the
the music industry okay that I mean
everybody listens to English English
language music American Music whatever
whatever genres you are fond of it's up
to you there is that uh then Nations
that perform well in
sports okay Jamaica is a tiny little
country but they have usan bold and
that's why people and they they have
their their quarted right the the relay
team the Sprint relative that does
really well so Nations that perform
really well in sport they are highly
admired you may not uh love those
Nations but you admire them you respect
them for their
achievements so all of these are
elements of soft power so when it comes
to India what is our biggest soft power
right now where is India admired for
what reasons is India admired if it is
so overall I would say that India
doesn't uh to be very honest India
doesn't have a great reputation uh
worldwide okay and some of it is because
of propaganda there's a lot of
propaganda online these days that seeks
to malign India and people see India as
a dirty Nation they still associate
India with open defecation because you
know there's been a lot of halalu in the
past 5 10 years about ending open
defecation and providing toilets to the
to the entire population so that has
brought this this previously existing
problem to the Forefront that there used
to be this problem in India open
defecation so today people see India as
that as a nation where this happens well
it doesn't happen anymore and then India
is regarded as a nation that's very
dirty and chaotic traffic and all that
stuff right there's a lot of negative uh
uh talk about India but if you were to
look at the positives now that we have
set the negatives aside and and dealt
with that if you were to look at the
positives India's great and most potent
um element of soft power is its culture
we are the oldest culture known oldest
known culture in the world the longest
continuously continuously existing
civilization in the world the Western
super hero genre has its roots and
origins in the Indian epics the
Mahabharat and the ramayan that those
were the original superheroes right the
great warriors Lord Ram Lord Krishna
karna and so on all the great Heroes of
the mahabarata ramayan those were the
original superheroes and even if you if
you go beyond that further back uh Gods
like Lord Indra Etc were the superheroes
Lord Indra is the god of the Thunderbolt
And The Hammer the template on which
Jupiter and Thor were built so our
culture is our greatest soft power but
we are not leveraging that our culture
manifests itself in so many ways our
Great temple architecture uh the great
monuments we have across Across the
Nation or length and breadth of the
nation uh our classical music our
theater forms our classical dances and
non-classical dances this classical
non-classical division in dances is
artificial I would say our indigenous
traditional dances folk dances and what
they uh class some people classify as
classical dances uh our literature but
all of this is dying today so the thing
about culture is that it needs you need
to be prosperous to build culture to
create culture to generate
culture uh if you look at the European
Renaissance it happened it happened as a
consequence of the great Prosperity that
that Venice and
Florence uh achieved during the Middle
Ages it's only when these places became
highly tremendously prosperous that the
Renaissance happened the cultural
Renaissance European Renaissance
and historically India the incredible
cultural output of India was only
possible because of the great wealth
India used to have and today India is
well a poor Nation per capita GDP is
very low it's a it's terribly
low uh and without State support for
Indian civilization civilization decays
so right now India's biggest soft power
ought to be its culture but there's
nothing being done to promote
culture uh and promotion of culture and
a new Resurgence florescence Renaissance
of Indian culture will happen only when
India becomes increasingly more
prosperous of course the government has
departments and Ministries and whatnot
dedicated to culture but they are not
doing their job okay to be very Frank to
be very honest so India's biggest soft
power ought to be India's culture
culture is your big soft power also we
if if we become better and better at
sport and we start achieving more in
sports then that's going to be another
element of our soft power if India
starts winning 2030 gold medals in the
Olympics then that that uh transforms
people's perception of the nation so all
of this put together is what constitutes
soft power India is doing a very poor
job just making slogans like incredible
India is not going to transform India
into an incred incredible nation is not
going to transform India's soft power
the government needs to invest real
money non-trivial sums of money into uh
promoting Indian culture tourism
Etc so that's not being done right now
and the the Ministries Etc exist but I'm
not sure if they are being run properly
and I would say they are the worst
performing ministers in India the
minister of culture
and you know even education is soft
power why do people why do students want
to go to the US or the UK or to stria
Australia or wherever else because these
Nations have a well until recently they
had excellent education systems don't
there there was a time in the ' 70s Etc
when India had a reasonably good
reputation in education and people from
African countries and Eastern Asian
countries would would come to India
students would come to India to study
but that's not the case anymore no one
ever comes to India anymore in instead
Indians go to even Nations like
Bangladesh and Ukraine and where not to
study so education can be another
element very powerful element of soft
power if we have a genuinely excellent
education system then the whole world
students from the entire world will
flock to you like we had in the past the
great universities in India
nilar vikam Shila URI so on so forth so
on so forth we currently are a nation of
low stands and that's why we don't have
too much soft power the perception the
overall reputation of India is overall
especially in the west it's kind of
negative okay and we need to change that
so that's the answer
that is the
answer okay
um some people someone's asking me my
opinions about some person listen I
don't talk about people I don't talk
about individual P people let's talk
about topics let's talk about issues
let's talk about Concepts what's the
point of discussing people I don't
discuss
people
uh okay pray Paul says starlink new
system direct to sell enables internet
connectivity for your mobile phone with
no extra equipment or special app will
musk Elon Musk succeed in beaming
starlink into
India H starlink is a is is a matter of
great concern for
India it's it's a matter of great
concern why is
that
uh starlink gives a foreign power the
ability to beam internet
directly into India directly to users
without any uh intermediary without any
government oversight without any
government regulation now you know you
would say lots of people in the west the
Libertarians would say that the less
government interference you have and the
less government roadblocks you have the
better it is for the people okay great
but this is a foreign power that is see
Elon Musk is not some individual in the
US he's the most powerful known person
in the US he probably is more powerful
at this time than Donald
Trump and they are in charge of the he's
in charge of the go Department of govern
governance government efficiency Doge
his number one minion is going to be
Vias Swami Etc right and they are saying
that they they're going after the Deep
state are you really sure about that I'm
pretty sure that Elon Musk actually is
the tip of the iceberg of the deep
State and what he's
doing is is in in a way Spearhead ing
America's transformation from a
superpower to a hyper power okay is
going to colonize Mars within the with
within the end probably by the end of
this decade we're GNA have humans on
Mars through star through space X so
Space X is going to
transform the US from a super power into
hyper power and starlink is going to
give the
US
unlimited
24x7 Global surveillance capabilities
it's going going to allow them to
penetrate Any Nation by passing all
government reg regulations they're doing
that in Brazil and uh I think it's two
or three years ago Elon Musk someone had
asked Elon Musk about the Brazilian
government's uh concern about
starlink and he said that they they can
howl at the sky which means that the the
government of Brazil can do a thing
about starlink and
some and in the past three four years he
had tweeted and then later deleted that
we will coup whoever we want so to me
it's you you guys must see it as as as
circumstantial evidence for me it's
pretty clear that Elon Musk is deep
State and he's going to end up being
more powerful than the president of the
US now this guy's going to beam internet
directly into into India and for some
reason the government of India seems to
be giving going ahead with giving him
approval for this you know what happens
let's say you have a bunch of rag tag
foreign cookie terrorists in Manipur who
are terrorizing the indigenous people of
Manipur now let's say some some incident
happens in the government imposes an
internet blackout for 48 hours or
whatever that happens right but what if
they have Starling
access it completely defeats what the
government is trying to do that's what's
been happening in
Ukraine right let's say you have some
riers a bunch of riers in some
City okay and there's a RI there's been
a riot and lots of tensions and and the
government imposes a cellular and
internet blackout for 48 hours and then
these people use tling to to communicate
and
coordinate and organize and plan and
execute what's the government going to
be able to
do by if the government of India goes
ahead and gives starlink the approval to
operate in India the government is
essentially digging India's own grave so
I don't know what the Narendra Modi
government is doing I hope that I that
whatever reports we are hearing are
incorrect I hope that starlink is not
allowed in India I'm sure there's going
to be arm twisting from the
Americans but if if India is still a
Sovereign Nation then I think the
government should not allow starlink to
operate in
India and like pray is saying this
direct to cell thing means that you take
a cell phone and you have Starling
directly accessible to you as long as
you are outside somewhere if you're
indoors you may not be able to receive
it but as long as you are under the Open
Sky
let's say you are a cookie terrorist
let's say you are a rioter let's say you
are a separatist somewhere somewhere
else plenty of anational elements in
India let's say you are one of the 100
million plus Bangladeshi infiltrators in
India who settled all across the country
you can use star link to organize to
coordinate to plan and execute all kinds
of stuff do we really want this I think
starlink is a huge danger for India I
hope the government of India doesn't
allow it to operate India otherwise we
are saying goodbye to our sovereignty
s SP Joker says India has overtaken UK
France Germany and Japan and GDP but in
terms of national wealth India is still
behind all these countries why is it so
and how what can India do to become the
wealthiest country in the world look
India's India is going to overtake Japan
soon so India is going to be soon I
think next year sometime next year 25
2025 sometime next year it is going to
be the fourth largest economy and then
it will sooner or later by 26 or 27
overtake Germany so India will become
the third largest economy now let's say
India has a GDP per capita of sorry
India has a total GDP perom of let's say
five uh trillion dollars five trillion
you divide that by India's population
which is 1.4 billion and you come it'll
give you a very low number so despite
having this very high GDP India will to
soon be the top three or top four India
when it comes to GDP per capita India is
ranked way way low which means the
living standards in India are very poor
and the people are poor overall the
average person is quite poor compared to
a person in Thailand for
example or a person living in
China or a person living in the West in
the UK or Japan or the us or
wherever uh so
that's that's the that's the problem
that India is facing so the great thing
is that we as a nation combined to have
this gigantic economy and uh as as long
as the economy keeps growing at whatever
rate is growing right now whatever the
current rate is if it keeps going
growing like that in the next 20 30
years India is going to be the one of
the top two
economies uh so that's great and once
India reaches something that's let's say
15 trillion 20 trillion then it's going
to be like three or four times then the
per capita GDP will also be three to
four times what it is now so then India
will become essentially a middle income
nation which will be great so what does
India have to do India has what can
India do to become the wealthiest
country in the world Well India has to
focus on
manufacturing uh India need to stop
exporting raw materials IND is to start
exporting finished products finished
products are way more valuable than the
raw materials that are they are made of
so India needs to do something India
needs to become a manufacturing power
now we have been talking about making
India for the past 10 years I'm sure we
have taken good steps in that direction
but uh we still have a lot to do and a
long way to go uh to achieve uh our full
potential so I would say that the most
important thing IND needs to do is to uh
becoming a
manufacturing major manufacturing power
which means that Indians should be
encouraged to set up manufacturing plans
and become entrepreneurs and all that
which means that the ease of doing
business in India needs to be improved
significantly way better than what it is
right now right now it is not that easy
to do business in India I'm sure India
is ranked 40th or what whatever rank it
is why aren't we ranked number one in
ease of doing
business or at least in the top 10 so
that's something the government needs to
work towards so if we do that then
things will get easier um interest rates
need to be cut a lot can be done okay
I'll not go into the details but the
crack of the issue is that we need to
become a manufacturing power major
manufacturing power ideally as good if
not better than China I know it's a it's
a big big thing to aim for but in 1990 2
or 1990 China where was China in
manufacturing
nowhere so if they could do it why can't
we do it it's possible but the
government needs to get it act together
I'm sure they're working on it okay
let's take a question from uh the
comments so I haven't seen this today in
the live chat the adani issue so shorts
with muai Mobi says ask allegations
against the adani group go to up adani
in American courts
what impact will this have on Indian
businesses
internationally okay so the uh some low
low ranking Court low level Court in the
US has uh made issued some issued a
charge sheet or something uh against uh
the adani group against Gotham adani
saying that they have given bribes
allegedly worth what half a billion
dollars uh to
government organizations or or arms of
the organs of the of the government in
India so the American court is saying
that
allegedly they are making the allegation
that the adani group gave bribes in
India to the to various Indian
government
organs now if let's assume
hypothetically in a hypothetical world
that this may this may allegedly have
happened okay hypothetically
it's happening in India right what
business do the American courts
have talking about India's internal
matters do they believe that their laws
are extra territorial they are
applicable across the world outside
their
territories in that case why do they why
do they keep on harping about the
rules-based world order the foundational
the first principle the foundational
pillar of the so-called rules based
World Order is National sovereignty
and non-interference that every nation
will be completely Sovereign and the
principle of non-interference is that no
Nation will interfere in the internal
affairs of other nations every nation is
free to manage its internal affairs on
its own without external interference
that's the foundational pillar of the
so-called westfalian order the
rules-based world order and the
Americans think that they can
now put their poke their fingers and
noses into the internal affairs of other
nations so that's the kind of thing
they're doing and they will probably
prosecute a case against Mr adani or
whatever I'm not sure what what the
course of action they're going to take
is but they piling on the pressure
against India now in this matter
now why is the adani group
important the adani
group it it takes up International
projects
and what kind of international projects
does it take it takes up International
projects that are aligned with India's
geopolitical interests for example the
adani group has
purchased the port purchased or taken
control for a certain number of years
the port in
haa Israel it's an extremely important
port they uh they manage mines uh coal
mines and what not other mines and all
kinds of such projects you know
Australia and other countries and where
not that are important to India
geopolitically
so so they are kind of working and and
some of these projects that they working
on have a certain amount of government
Indian government share in that so all
these projects are important to India
geopolitically that's why the adani
group is is important it's it's
essentially you could say
say a tool or an
arm of India's geopolitical uh strategy
to a certain extent and it is not doing
anything illegal it is doing everything
legally right but now the Americans have
done that and then the Kenyans have have
cancelled a big contract that they had
awarded to the adani group
uh and there are looks like there are
certain let's say elements within India
that are very pleased with uh what has
with what has
happened they are very pleased and it
looks like some of these elements uh may
have linkages to foreign governments
let's just say let's just put it like
that I'm not naming anybody so okay I'm
not naming anyone but there are lots of
elements in India that seem to have very
straightforward clear linkages with
foreign governments maybe source of
funding or
whatever and they seem to be working
against the interests of the national
interests of
India now there are a lot of uh
influencers also who are who keep on
demonizing adani and they play on the
Indian the average Indian person's
mistrust of wealth now what do I mean by
mistrust of
wealth in the 20th century after 1947
the uh various regimes like the nean
regime Etc they imposed a very strictly
socialistic form of government in India
the the economic model was Fabian
socialism it was almost impossible to
start a business in India you had to get
hundreds of approvals and you had to
wait negotiate all kinds of red tape and
even if you succeeded in starting a
business in India you had to allegedly
pay bribes to all inspectors and baboos
and bureaucrats and politicians and
whatnot and the effect of that was that
it was impossible to run a business
profitably unless you were fortunate
enough to have very high level
Connections in which case you would pay
off your high level connections and they
would allow you to make a profit in a
win-win kind of
scenario and these these fortunate few
who had the high level connections they
would go ahead and prosper and they
would treat their workers very poorly in
those days it was very it was very hard
to gain employment in India so if you
are a worker in one of these factories
or Mills or whatever then it was you
would see that as a great blessing and
even if you are paid a pittance you
would do your best to hang on to the job
because otherwise you would be on the
street so they would exploit the workers
terribly so it was was n and and and so
it was natural for Indians to see
anybody who was wealthy in the 20th
century it was natural for for Indians
to see them as probably being
crooked so if someone was wealthy you
would say ah this guy must be indulging
in some kind of skull dugery or some
kind of corruption corrupt corrupt
activities so and therefore so the
overall thing was that it was impossible
for a common honest person to become
even middle class in India okay you
would at best be lower middle
class and then you would have
bureaucrats who would be doing
government jobs and who would have all
this who would have all this wealth
Bungalows and cars and whatnot so in
India wealth was seen as something that
was evil and wealth was seen as
something you could achieve only by
being corrupt and crooked and
evil and that perception unfortunately
still exists
today now today things have changed
today it is possible for people to
become wealthy without indulging in
corruption but those old attitudes still
persist and for good reason even today
if any if you see bureaucrats and
politicians who have these I don't know
what before elections the the
politicians have to declare their wealth
right the minimum amount of wealth will
be 20 30 CRS for for a random local
politician how on Earth does a
politician acquire so much
wealth right and then you have
bureaucrats today also allegedly some
okay I'm not saying all I'm not saying
all politicians either but a lot of
bureaucrats have wealth that is hard to
account for it's beyond their their
income right so that's why even today
people see wealth as something evil if
you are wealthy it means that you must
have done something crooked something
corrupt and that's why when when people
like Amani adani get really really
wealthy people see them as as being the
epitome of whatever you know they they
can't see them as as being honest
individuals so uh that's why there is a
lot of
uh let's
say misinformation out there uh I think
Mr adani is a reasonably self-made man
he he is you know put in all the hard
yards he has paid his dues I'm pretty
sure uh and whatever projects he is
doing are in in synchronicity with the
Indian national interest so I think we
should support him and support the adani
group because it's it's good for India
uh but yeah this is the situation that
we are facing right now that the Adon
group has been you know the Americans
have opened a case against it and
they've alleged that they have paid
bribes and maybe the Americans could go
after other Indian businesses that are
also in synchronicity with the Indian
interest okay so as long as you are a
business person and you're not doing
something that helps India they will
leave you alone but if you are a big
business person and you are
operating projects that are helping
India directly or indirectly in a
geopolitical manner they they're going
to Target
you that's what you will face but if
you're a person of Indian origin and
doing your own business and it has
nothing to do with India then you'll be
left alone that is how it's going to be
played
okay
uh okay where was
this allegation on adani will result on
loss of trust on Indian business um
we'll see about that mclin says did you
see the N goth fight no one said that no
one is talking about him yeah so Netflix
right that horrid Netflix live stream
that
was that was a very poor live stream it
was it was impossible to watch uh
especially during the Tyson versus Jake
Paul Jake Paul Logan Paul one of those
two guys that fight Jake Paul probably
and and in the runup to the fight there
were three or four other fights and NJ
goth fought some some guy I forget his
name and he won so yeah it's good that
he won it was a professional fight and
he defeated his opponent so good on him
and hope to see him do better going
forward and yeah people were all hyped
up about about the Tyson Mike Tyson
fight so no one was talking about this
but um I'm glad you you noticed
that okay what other questions I I don't
do any Indian politics I have no idea
okay see I mean I appreciate you asking
me this question but I am no expert on
Indian politics I don't follow Indian
politics I don't see the seat seat share
and vote share and all that I have no
idea I look at international relations
geopolitics not in Indian politics I
never comment about Indian politics
because I'm no expert so I won't be able
to answer this question sorry about
that
uh kro anush shiran says who's your
favorite mathematician and Theorem
that's a great question uh so many great
mathematicians L leard Oiler um gregori
Perman who's still
alive uh obviously Shas ramanujan so
many more probably my favorite
mathematician would be ramanujan because
he was like ah Hardy also the guy who
for the west from the Western
perspective the guy who discovered
ramanujan uh he was another great
mathematician but he considered himself
a nobody compared to someone like
ramanujan according to him ramanujan was
the greatest of all and he wrote about
this in his book his
autobiography and the autobiography is
called a mathematician's
apology hardy hardy and little wood his
his most frequent
collaborator uh so I would say probably
my favorite mathematician would be
ramanujan in the modern era of course
you had lots of ancient mathematicians
madav of s
sagam uh
nilak basar arara rahma Gupta so many
more so many more
pingala uh pingala is the guy who came
up with the so-called uh what's it
called Fibonacci series the Fibonacci
series is the pingala series okay it's
not the Fibonacci series it's the
pingala series and so on uh my favorite
uh
theorem uh there are so many theorems I
okay the first time I I understood what
people meant about beauty in
mathematics was when I saw the McLaren
series I was probably in student the
mcen series what is the McLaren series
it's incredibly beautiful I mean that's
the first time I could understand what
people meant by the beauty of
mathematics so let let's let's try and
Google it quickly mlen theor Series in
case you want to understand what I mean
by that so let me let's go to our friend
Google and let's let's Google mclen
series okay so we can go to Wolf from
math
world and this one right it's a tailor
series expansion of function about zero
so f of x is f of 0 plus FR Prime of 0
which is the first derivative of the
function around 0 plus the second
derivative around 0id 2 factorial * x s
and so on so forth it's incredibly
beautiful the first time I saw Beauty
and I understood that mathematics is
indeed beautiful so maybe that that's
that's the one I would say I mean I it's
it's actually a pretty rudimentary kind
of theorem the Taylor series is the real
deal but yeah if you want ask me that
the first time I saw I I glimpsed Beauty
for the first time in mathematics that
was the McLaren series McLaren theorem
whatever want to call it uh okay let's
see more some more
questions
um Karthik a says do you think the Deep
State wants to depopulate the world
um well
um you know that globally if you look at
the global TFR overall it's declining
for sure for some countries it is pretty
high I believe in Israel the TFR is
significantly above 2.1 in various
African nations the TFR total fertility
rate is way above 2.1 but in all
industrialized countries and Industrial
izing countries the total fertility rate
is is dropping in Europe it must be
around 1.5 see the total fertility rate
is the average is the number of children
the average woman has in her lifetime in
a nation so let's say you have a nation
with 100 million people okay
hypothetically out of that let's say
there are 50 million women then the
total fertility rate is if it is two it
means that these 50 million women will
each have on average two children
and uh you need a TFR of 2.1 for
whatever your population currently is to
be sustained if the TFR drops below 2.1
the population starts
declining so it starts dropping over
time slowly gradually if your total
fertil fertility rate is 1.5 that's
dangerous if it is so it's it's almost
crisis likee in Nations like Japan it's
1.2 or something Korea it's disastrous
it's around one China also it was 1 1 or
1.2 which is another disaster in India
it's become 2.0 in some states it is 1.7
1.6 India India is is facing an
impending crisis if this continues now
some people will say that yeah
population India's population is too
high we need to decrease it I agree 1.4
billion is way too much for India the
ideal population is about 300 million
which we used to have historically but
you can't suddenly drastically drop your
TFR the population will start dropping
but the average age of the population
will start increasing do you want want
to have a country where the average
person is 60 years old do you understand
how disastrous that is so if you want to
drop your population to a reasonable
level let's say 500 million or 300
million that needs to be a two Century
long project you can't do it in 20 30 40
50 years it has to be a two Century
project you to do it very gradually
otherwise you'll be facing disaster
China is going to face it demographic
disaster so lots of nations are facing
this the total fertility rate is has
dropped drastically especially in
Nations where you have this this
extremely H hard work work ethic work
Works work work 100 hours a week don't
take days off if you work a 100 hours a
week or let's say 70 hours a week okay
let's some people say Indians should
work 70 hours a week I'm okay with that
but understand if the husband and the
wife both work 70 hours a week they're
going to be exhausted will they be will
they have the energy to procreate or
even if they manage to procreate who's
going to take care of their kids in the
metropolitan cities where you have
nuclear families so because of that the
TFR is decreasing in in in metropolitan
cities and states which have higher
incomes in places like Korea where
people work themselves work like crazy
the total fertility rate has declined
drastically same with Japan and the same
in various European nations in the US
they're going to offset that by bringing
in migrants
uh so I don't know about whether the
Deep state is doing this but one of the
side effects of a capitalist economy is
dropping TFR is that the TFR drops in a
capitalist economy you it's all about
profits quarter upon quarter profits
every quarter you need profits otherwise
the stay shareholders will drop your
shares so if you pursue quarter upon
quarter profits on infinite profits on a
finite Planet you will destroy the
planet and you will also destroy your
population
so I don't know if it's a deep state or
whatever I don't know it's if it's a
conspiracy of
sorts um there could be other elements
that people talk about I'm aware of the
the MRNA elements and all that but uh
the overall thing we are seeing is that
the world is going to see a population
collapse if things continue the same way
I don't know the Deep state is behind
that okay I don't have sufficient
evidence to point in One Direction or
the other but this is certainly
something that is some that is happening
you know a population decline Elon Musk
says it's population collapse I think
he's talking about an as asymptotic
solution population collapse over the
next 30 40 50 years but in the next 10
20 years you're going to see declining
populations over a 50 year horizon 50e
horizon you may see population collapse
also which is not good because then you
will be left with Nations where the
majority where the average person is an
elderly person then who's going to run
the
economy who's going to continue who's
going to carry the flag forward into the
future there's going to be no one left
so that's why we need to be very careful
about these
things it's okay to work really hard but
you got to have kids and take care of
these kids well and raise them
well geopolitical du says how did
ancient Egyptians have so many so much
gold and wealth there were no gold mines
far fing of crude oil production at the
time what did they use to trade I'm not
very uh familiar with the Egyptian
economy they do not have so much gold or
wealth uh if you compare Egypt ancient
Egypt with ancient India the Indian GDP
of the time would have dwarfed the
Egyptian GDP uh okay this is a good uh
opportunity to take a look at the map so
where is our friend Z map yes where's
the map here's the
map understand this let's say we talking
about 2,000 BC or or 3,00 3,000 BC okay
let's say we're talking about 3,000 BC
so the Egyptian Empire was from about
3,000 BC to about 3 332 BC when
Alexander destroyed it or or conquered
it so let's say we are talking about
2,500 BC it's the time when we had the
sarasa Hindu phase of our history very
large fa very large population uh we had
in in northern and western India
and we had Egypt so Egypt the Egyptian
civilization was centered around just
one River the Nile everything else in
Egypt is Desert understand this there's
only one tongue of green and the
entirety of Egyptian civilization was
based around this one River the
population was low it wasn't a large
population and the overall wealth was
nothing compared to the wealth that
India had okay uh so I I would not agree
that Egypt had incredible amounts of
wealth and gold and all that they were a
good reasonably powerful Empire they
fought the hit Tides they fought the
bani they fought the the the the hiu
they fought everybody else and they were
the major power in the region there were
no other empires of any any consequence
or significance in the region beside the
Egyptians um and if they had gold they
would probably be be sourcing it from
other parts of Africa and perhaps
through trade with with other uh
geopolitical entities like the bani um
the the the
Hittites uh and whoever else probably
India as well because India used to
trade with them we we have Indian zebu
cattle in Egypt to around 2,000 BC so it
it would probably be through trade India
acquired most of its gold through trade
with other countries we would say sell
them our spices and finished products
you know uh finished products like
textiles and all kinds of other things
and they would give us gold so generally
uh if a if a
doesn't have gold mines but it has gold
it means it's acquiring it through trade
or through force from somewhere else
okay either through trade or by conquest
by force now uh for
example well let me give you an example
that is a little controversial it will
upset some people but it is what it is
does France have any gold mines France
has no gold mines but they have a
tremendous amount of gold where does the
gold come from gold comes from Western
Africa where all these countries have
gold mines but they don't
they don't keep any of the gold it all
goes to France it's called neoc
colonization so I'm not an expert on
Egyptian economy okay uh but uh you they
would either have acquired it by by
trading with other nations or by
Conquest you conquer a play a country
which has gold mines and you extract the
gold and you acquire that those are the
two ways so it would probably be a
combination of both but in Africa gold
is found in Western Africa I'm not sure
if the Egyptians had contacts western
Africa Africa is a gigantic continent uh
so probably through trade or Conquest
they did conquer uh various other
Kingdoms in various times and so
on okay thas thres Comas says could AI
crack Tri time travel since it literally
can access literally can access data
from any point in recorded history can
it figure out possible future
timelines see the see AI
systems it can they can access whatever
you make available to
them if you give an AI system access to
the internet then it can access whatever
is available in the public domain which
means not behind a pay wall or any other
wall
uh there will be data that is not
available on on the internet there will
be data that's safeguarded
there'll be data that's firewalled it it
can't access that unless it has figured
out how to crack everything okay hack
hack into everything which could be
possible but maybe not let's say you
have data in a vault that is air gapped
there's no way eii can access that uh
there are lots of ancient texts Etc
manuscripts and so and so on that have
never been digitized they only exist in
physical form and they're crumbling
let's say in India we have several
million ancient mon many ancient
manuscripts Etc that are written on Palm
leaves and all that are crumbling away
in the Indian archives and nobody gives
a damn about that I mean from the ASI
from the historial perspective no one no
one cares they just don't care that our
heritage is wasting away so AI can't
access that so AI has access has access
to a limited sub subset of the overall
data that exists worldwide not all the
data a smaller subset of the actual
amount of information that
exists but AI learns and AI can
certainly make inferences in so on uh So
based on whatever data is available to
it can AI crack trime time
travel to crack time travel you have
to well that's that's that's a problem
in
physics and according to some U
solutions to the Einstein field
equations in general relativity time
travel may be theoretically possible but
practically it's not possible
practically because we don't have the
technology to do what is
required uh we don't have the ability to
create wormholes and if we even have a
wormhole we don't have the ability to
keep them open because they want to
snapshot the neck wants to snapshot the
throat of the Wormhole for that you
would need exotic matter like negate
matter with negative mass or or
something even weirder than that which
is those primordial cosmic strings which
we have never observed if you have that
then you could keep a ver open and you
could and then you would
need uh then you would need Rel istic
travel and then you may have certain
situations in which you may end up at a
different point in time that sort of
thing okay I'm just giving you a very
very cursory view view of what the
theory is uh so this is a physics
problem time travel is a physics problem
it's not about accessing ancient
data for AI to be able to crack time
travel you would need a very intelligent
AI so uh we may soon be at a point where
you where some of these AI systems could
become AI artificial general
intelligence which is the equivalent of
a human being with let's say 130 140 IQ
which is a reasonably intelligent human
being so those AI systems could could
conceivably think on their own and solve
problems that have never been solved
before at the level of a person of with
130 140 IQ that's artificial general
intelligence with AGI you can't solve
time travel because if that was the case
then anybody with 130 140 IQ who applies
himself or herself in physics for a
certain amount of time 10 20 30 years
will be able to solve the problem but
time travel is not that sort of problem
so AGI artificial general intelligence
won't be able to solve it but
then there's another stage of AI which
is
ASI which is artificial super
intelligence and that is the equivalent
of a person with maybe 350 or 500 IQ
such humans don't exist if you have that
sort of IQ then you can solve problems
that you can't even
imagine that that sort of AI may solve
time trouble and may make it
possible it may allow you to create
wormholes and and keep them open and so
so on so forth so if ASI happens it may
solve the the problem of Time problem
possibly it may be able to create
technologies that appear to us like
magic technologies that that deep in the
realm of Science Fiction only ASI can do
it AGI can't do it uh so we may or may
not have ASI right now look in the
public domain you have what what
anthropic Ai and Cloe Ai and chat GPT Ai
and perplexity Ai and grock AI all these
things these are like children's
toys it's it's it's like a
stunted toned down version of the real
AI that that
exists uh they give you a small flavor
of it uh the real power of the AI that
exists currently is going to is
currently being used by the US
government they are using the full
version of the AI whatever is available
in the public domain is just like 23% of
the real capabilities so they won't give
that access to excuse me they won't give
access to that to people like us to the
ordinary people so it's possible that
AGI may already have been achieved D in
secret and the next step is ASI so I
don't know if it's um like these UFOs
that you see that that you see in the US
uh I don't think they're aliens I think
that's advanced technology that is
secret similarly there'll be that sort
of technology in the realm of AI which
would be secret and which will not be
revealed to the public so such AI
systems could be able to crack certain
problems maybe even time travel if you
if it is an ASI system
and such systems may possibly be able to
figure out possible future outcomes
possible future outcomes not guaranteed
future outcomes but possible Super
Future outcomes and they may be able to
assign various probabilities to these
various outcomes and tell you what is
the most likely outcome it's like
playing a game of hyper chess in chess
you have 64 squares right and Grand
Masters can think 10 15 moves in ADV in
advance can think ahead 10 15 moves but
an ASI system could think ahead 10 R to
15 moves one with 15 zeros after it that
sort of thing you know so yeah there we
have it okay let's take another
question from the comments and this is a
question by Mr
8ers how did Russia retain the permanent
seat in the UN Security Council when the
USSR disintegrated didn't the west or
the USA try to block Russia I mean they
had the opportunity to run the agenda
that UNC permanent SE belongs to the sov
sovereign state of the USSR and Russia
is a totally different state or
something like that so what really
happened this is an excellent question
how come nobody has asked me this
question before how come nobody has
asked
me so what happened we know I hope we
know that the USSR collapsed in late
1991 right late 91 is when the USSR
collapsed and the various uh Central
Asian uh republics declared independence
usbekistan Tajikistan kazakistan kistan
blah blah blah all all these nations
okay like there were and they formed
something called The Commonwealth of
independent states the CIS and there
were 12 members of the
CIS
so in late
1991 11 out of these 12 CIS member
states they signed a
declaration and they said that the
member states of the
CIS
agree they don't agree they support
Russia in taking over the USSR
membership in the United Nations
including permanent membership in the
security
Council so they signed this and then the
USA then the United Nations agreed to uh
have Russia replace the USSR and then
things continued the way they did now
there have been questions about the
legality of all this and all but it it
by the time it was a faith ACC comply
and it was just already done so it's
because that it's because the CIS the
Commonwealth of independent states 11
out of the 12 members supported
Russia as a replacement for the US USSR
that's why Russia became Russia retained
or Russia took over the ussr's permanent
seat in the UN Security Council now the
question the good question over here is
that why did the US or the West not try
to block Russia excellent question right
and and that's that's what makes this
question
interesting who cares about these small
Nations I mean small and mostly
powerless Nations signing this
memorandum or
whatever so what if the Big Daddy the US
vetos this proposal then it's all over
right because in the UN Security Council
just one person one member out of the
five vetoing something is game over so
what really
happened this happened Russia was able
to do this only because the US was okay
with it see what happened when the USSR
disintegrated is that mik gorbachov lost
power the nation
disintegrated and what was left was
Russia the Russia that we have today and
gorbachov lost power and who came to
power Boris yelon
and Boris yelson and gorbachov are both
seen as us
Stooges okay after the US are
disintegrated gorbachov appeared in a
Pizza Hut
Commercial saying that you
know the USSR has gone so what we have
Great American Pizza now let's enjoy
it and Boris yelson what he did was that
he destroyed the Russian economy uh to
summarize everything in just one
sentence okay he he was instrumental in
destroying the Russian economy so he was
essentially a US
asset so when you have a nation newly
created Nation with your asset running
it why will you not allow that Nation
to uh to join to to to gain the ussr's
permanency in the UN Security Council so
I'm sure it was not a good move even at
that time even even if their puppet was
in power in the USSR because longterm
who knows but I think at that point in
time the US was going through this
moment of hubris this was the great
unipolar moment they had won the Cold
War they had defeated the USSR at that
point in time that they probably thought
they are
invincible and that's why they made the
mistake of allowing Russia to take over
uh the ussr's permanent seat in the UN
Security Council I'm pretty sure that
it's considered to be mistake now but
that is what happened and then as we
know we know what happened later in
history uh Boris elsen was a drunkard
and a very bad president who did lots of
blunders he lost the first Chen war and
eventually he was replaced by an unknown
guy called Vladimir Putin and then the
rest is
history so this is a great
question all right
okay I will not take Manipur questions
today I have spoken a lot about it um
and there's no serious progress in it so
what's the point I'll I'll not discuss
Manipur today I know people are asking I
app appreciate your questions but I have
spoken a lot about it uh uh once again
let me remind you that
uh where is
that let me let me remind you all that
uh about the
live about the about the short clips
channel so I have a short short clips
Channel called abijit Chava clips and uh
you can see the previous questions have
answered uh on that channel if I can
find it it's over here once again in in
case many of you have joined later this
is the short clips Channel all the
questions I answer on these live streams
these are chopped up into individual
questions and answers and they are put
up on this channel the abijit ch Clips
channel so you have this question from
episode 217 this is a question from
episode 218 this is from 217 and you
will have uh you know questions from
other episodes 214 214 here this is also
214 and so on so forth okay so in case
you want to see my previous answers you
can find them here I'm pretty sure there
are there are questions about Manipur
here kiland for Christ over here and U
so I've spoken in depth about these
matters
uh so you can find all of that over
there okay now let's take some of
questions
uh okay let's see what else
um
uh prasa goam says what kind of role did
the Nazis play in the formation of NASA
and NATO is it true that us used Nazi
intelligence to cter the Soviets so
after the end of the second world war a
bunch of these high ranking Nazi uh
officers members of adulf Hitler's uh
Inner Circle Etc where obviously they
they were they were captured they were
arrested they were put on trial the
nurenberg trials and a whole bunch of
them were hanged over there hanged as a
consequence of being found guilty of
various crimes various war
crimes that happened but many of them
were not funny
and many of them went on to play
significant roles in nato in NASA so
let's go to our friend Google one more
time where is Google and let us Google a
couple of people one is
Adolf
hinger who is this gentleman Adolf
hinger the former Inspector General of
the bundas V
um his this guy was a German military
officer whose career spammed the German
Empire the viar Republic Nazi Germany
West Germany and
NATO
[Music]
uh uh he served as the chairman of the
NATO military committee from 1961 to 64
okay
uh he was the operations Chief within
the the general staff of the high
command of the Nazi German Army in the
vak from 1938 to 1944 so this guy was a
clear Nazi and he became the chairman of
the NATO military committee can you
believe that yes here he is with the US
foreign secretary Robert McNamara in
Washington DC
1964 isn't that interesting NATO Adolf
hinger that's just one example okay
let's let's
uh uh Google another
guy what was his
name H Saturn I forget the guy's name
he's a very very very famous name Saturn
V chief
engineer sat
five ah verer Von Brown the great man
the Pioneer the father of the rocket in
of of modern rocketry great rocket
engineer Verner Von
Brown so this guy well he worked for the
Nazis he was the guy who developed the
first ever cruise
missile okay and also the first ever
ballistic missile the first cruise
missile was what the V1 I believe uh
career in
Germany experiment Cruise Miss okay the
V1 and the V2 were the so the V2 is is
the first B bistic missile and the V1 or
the the Bumble what Doodlebug V1 where
is the V1 there's no V1
here
[Music]
Doodlebug okay okay so so he developed
the V1 the V2
Rockets great rocket scientist
eventually he was captured by the he
surrendered to the Americans he was
taken cap prisoner essentially he was uh
moved to the United States and he EV
became the head of
NASA okay let's see what it says here
okay space architect etc etc and a
Pioneer what does it say about his
career in NASA
is uh he was the chief architect of the
set five Super heavy super heavy lift
launch
vehicle and so on he what was his career
in NASA he was the boss in NASA wasn't
he so this is him in NASA with his
rockets and so on so uh that's another
guy ver V Brown so when it comes to NASA
NASA pioneered the entire American Space
Program they did it with German
technology it was all German technology
the Americans developed none of this
technology from scratch they captured a
bunch of German missiles they moved them
shipped them to the United States
captured a bunch of German rocket
Engineers such as V Brown and his people
and these guys are the ones that that
created the American Space Program when
it comes to Nazi to to Nato a bunch of
Nazis in there at least one we know of
Adolf heisinger so very interesting
history and uh yeah that's the
history okay now let's let's uh take
another
question
from one second okay let's take a
question from the comments once
again so this is by Tech wise 360 where
do you see the Russians in the next few
months as the West has crossed the red
line by Supply supplying Ukraine with
long-range missiles and using them
against Russia look the Ukraine war is
now has now seemingly entered a new
phase the West has the Biden regime
which is a lame duck regime because
they've lost the election and Trump is
going to be in power in office at least
from January something onwards 21 or
something onwards in a couple of months
so the Biden regime is a lame duck
regime Biden Biden is a lame duck
president they are currently
transitioning they are doing the
transition to the Trump
regime and in despite being a lame duck
regime that has lost the elections they
are going ahead and pouring fuel on the
fire in Ukraine so they have given the
go-ahead to Ukraine for using uh long
range American missiles and the Russians
say that the ukrainians don't have the
ability to use these missiles which
means that you will need American
technicians on the ground who will oper
operate the missiles and actually send
them off fire
them but yeah such missile strikes have
already started there is a new phase in
the new escalated new escalation in the
war I think the Russians will uh not
take any drastic action any any any very
drastic
measures until Trump comes to power and
then they will
probably be expecting the Trump will
negotiate with them and seek to find
ways and solutions that will lead
towards an end to this war or some kind
of ceasefire so I think the Russians
will try and wait it out and in the
meanwhile it looks like the Biden regime
will try their best to instigate the
Russians to escalate by escalating
themselves um so I think the next couple
of months are going to be very uh
dangerous because the Biden regime seems
to be hellbent on on on on instigating
nuclear
war uh so I think the Russians despite
whatever is being said about Putin and
Russia in the western media I think the
Russians are super sane they're very
logical people Putin is a very logical
rational sane person he understands what
the Biden regime wants to instigate him
into doing and he will make sure that he
doesn't allow them to succeed
so yeah that's the kind of stage of the
war that we are
in okay
uh some other questions I saw something
somewhere
um I think there was a question about I
don't know where is
it okay let's go back to that question
itself
okay okay not this one this one right
and a continuation of that is that
Russia allegedly used an
ICBM just a few days ago against Ukraine
so the America so the ukrainians with
American help with help American help
and American approval they uh
targeted sites in Russia with American
longrange missiles and Russia responded
by launching at least one ballistic
missile attack against Ukraine now the
media reported that this was an ICBM
intercontinental ballistic
missile
now let's take a look at the
map
okay uh here's Ukraine and here's
Russia
now InterContinental missile
have a range in excess of 8,000 km let's
say you are launching a missile from
let's say some position like this here
uh Saratov o blast wherever it was what
what location was it I don't remember
right now but you see if you want to
hypothetically Target uh a place in the
interior of Ukraine then that's just
about 500 or so kilometers from
reasonably within Russian territory so
for targeting a location that's 500 600
7 let's say th000 kilms away you don't
use an intercontinental ballistic
missile that's a waste of a missile
those missiles are insanely
expensive you don't use an ICBM for that
you use a medium range
missile so Putin later went ahead and
gave a statement that um that they had
used a new
medium- range ballistic missile to
Target Ukraine it's a new experimental
developmental test of the missile I
forget the name of the missile it's in
Russian but it's an intermediate or
medium range ballistic missile and
apparently it may have had mirvs
multiple independently targetable
re-entry Vehicles so one missile with
five packages or 10 packages in it so a
missile a missile that carries multiple
Warhead heads and can Target each
Warhead independently of the others that
sort of
thing um now ballistic missiles can be
used to deliver regular payloads as well
as nuclear payloads in this case it was
obviously not nuclear payloads it was
just regular uh low explosive payload
because I saw the footage it was not
like big explosions it was about sending
a
message not to Ukraine but to the US and
apparently there is a hotline between
Russia and the US and the Russians used
it just a few
minutes before the launch just just
before the launch and they informed the
Americans in advance that we are going
to do this and this is a non-nuclear
missile it's not going to have nuclear
nuclear warheads but we're just
informing you so that there is no
unnecessary escalation or
Panic so the Russians have taken this
measure which demonstrates that they
have options in the in the escalation
ladder the they don't have only one
option which is tactical nuclear
warheads they have multiplicity of
options and they have a new missile that
they can use new ballistic missile that
they can use so yeah this is an
escalation in the war the Americans are
trying their best to
to to send us headlong into nuclear war
uh but the
Russians I think they are holding firm
and hopefully once Trump comes in power
uh things will change and hopefully the
war ends in know some kind of ceasefire
hopefully okay
um what else what else what else uh
feminist Slayer say did studying history
full of Deceit selflessness and War ever
make you feel disheartened about human
nature and the world how did you cope
with these harsh truths and the red pill
Awakening look you will be disheartened
if you have certain Illusions about
human nature if you have a utopian
idealistic view of human nature if you
are if you imagine or if you believe
that human nature is all about good and
peace and nonviolence and then you read
history and you see the opposite then
you will be disheartened disillusioned
etc for me I have never had these qualms
about human nature I've never had the
the
these
um I've never had these wrong ideas
about human nature I'm I have always
been a realistic person I've always
understood that human nature is complex
it's complicated and I've been reading
history since I was a kid and I always
saw that history is mainly about
Warfare so that tells us that human
history human nature hasn't changed in
thousands of years we have always been
that way and we are still going we still
that way and we will probably remain
that way it's just part of what we are
that's human nature I think it's
genetically wired into us because of the
harsh realities of The evolutionary
process uh sink or swim survival of the
fittest and all that that you have to
compete for
survival so yeah so that's that's part
of human nature so I have I am very much
aware that human history is full of
Deceit like you say deceit selflessness
and war and
violence it's never made me feel
disheartened it's it's just what it is
it's just a fact it's just a reality
what's there to be disheartened about um
of course we can aspire to be better
than that and there have been times in
human history where we have had
civilizations that
have um been civilized in in the in the
sense that even during Warf there would
be rules and such civilized behavior and
such rules eventually led to these
civilizations being defeated I'm talking
about us obviously India right I mean in
India when two Kingdom would go to war
they would never touch civilians they
would never touch Farmers it was was
always soldiers fighting soldiers in the
rest of the world in Europe it's a the
civilians are fair
game uh there's this guy his name was
Gom he was known pardon my French he was
known as William the
bastard okay and he was a Norman Duke he
was the fourth or fifth or whatever Duke
of Norman
Normandy and we're talking about the
11th century he was he was an
illegitimate child and he became the
Duke because his father did not have any
other options so he had to made an make
an illegitimate son his his successor as
the Duke of Normandy so this guy William
the
bastard in his
50s he assembles a fleet of ships and a
resonably big army and he crosses the
English Channel crosses from Normandy
into England across the English Channel
invades England gets really lucky and
wins defeats the English King Harold and
he becomes the king of England and from
then onwards he's onwards he's known as
William the Conqueror and this was the
Battle of
Hastings Hastings or Stamford Bridge
Hastings Battle of
Hastings um 1066
ad now this guy William the Conqueror
was known as a very Pious man Etc now as
he Grew Older for some reason he became
really fat and he had a really really
big tummy okay
happens now his Overlord in France when
he was Duke was the King of France and
the King of France made a really
distasteful joke about William the
Conqueror he he he compared William the
Conqueror to a woman who is pregnant
very distasteful joke so William got
really offended really really offended
and he crossed over into France he
invaded France and let me show you where
this happened okay there's a city called
MTH where is MTH it's in France let's go
out zoom in okay okay this is where moth
is okay so he comes to the city of moth
which is a nice pretty city with nice
landmarks and
all and he sacks the
city and he has everybody killed he
burns the church and the people inside
the
church and he said it is fair game
because these people who I'm killing are
part of the insult that was offered to
me so this happened in moth now when the
city was burning a flying piece of coal
came and his horse stepped on
it and because of the pain his horse R
up on it on its hind legs and the pommel
of the saddle it pressed into William's
sto stomach and burst his
bowels and this led to his
excruciatingly painful death a few days
later that's how William the Conqueror
died and I showed you where this
happened in the city of moth now his
actions are brutal barbaric but part of
the rules of war in Europe in that
culture in
Christendom it's part of the culture
that if another country's King insults
me I have the right to go and fight him
which is fine but I have the right to to
kill his citizen the citizens of the
country because they are part of the
insult that was offered to me so if you
study history you will come across so
many examples like these and that is
just the harsh reality of human nature
and warfare and we in India have we
tried to live by different rules and
those rules because we our Kings adhered
to them unquestioningly and blindly even
when faced with barbarians that's why we
got defeated if Johan had been ruthless
and if other rajput kings and other
other kings had been ruthless and
treated The
Barbarians like animals not like like
civilized people then the outcomes would
have been
different so the point is we should be
aware of human nature we should be aware
of what others are capable of and and
don't let that make you feel
disheartened well it's just what it is
facts are facts facts don't care about
anyone's feelings so there we have it
um okay aay Sharma says I once had a got
the chance to meet an ex KGB agent in
his 60s and he told me that they have
documents that was that show that Hitler
was put in regime by the British any
thoughts look I don't know
um I have not seen anything that points
in that direction directly
uh there are some coincidences in in
vietna there was a time when Hitler and
various other people Carl Marx Etc they
were all living a few me 100 meters from
each other in one place there are some
coincidences like that but I'm not sure
about this this claim that Hitler was
brought to Power by the British I'm not
sure about
that
okay um
okay dr's game says what do you think
about Sigman
FY what is he even famous
for uh the most famous theory of
psychosexual evolution has no empirical
evidence what should one do with
interest in Psychology
study um there's going to be people who
don't like what I say I think psychology
is
voodoo psychology is all assumptions
some of it may work to a certain extent
look psychology is about studying what
your mind right it's about understanding
the mind now we know for a
fact that our mind doesn't reside in our
ear or our nose or in our thumbs right
or any other part of the body the Mind
resides here in the brain we know
that so the organ we are studying is the
brain now when you have psych
psychological Psych atric problems or
whatever
um do they scan your
brain no do do we even know properly
where feelings and thoughts and
behavioral patterns arise from what part
of the brain we not quite sure we know
roughly that sound that's the sensory
cortex does certain things that there is
an ala olfactory part of the brain there
is an auditory part of the brain we know
where vision is processed you know the
the optic nerves they go behind and
cross over like this and then go into
the visual cortex and so on we know
roughly where these things happen
but thoughts feelings emotions
behavioral patterns how do those arise
and why do they go wrong at times and
why do certain people have certain
issues we have no idea we have no
clue so when you have a fracture you're
going to get an x-ray and get your arm
or whatever portion of your body is
fractured you're going to have it scan
and then you can fix it if you if you if
you have heart disease for example
they're going to scan your heart and do
that you know that injected Dy into your
vein and you know see where the
blockages are and all that and the same
goes for other parts of the body you get
CT scans done and sonographies done and
various kinds of Imaging and all that
when it comes to the problems of the
mind we don't map the brain we don't we
don't study the brain brain of the
person
that's that is the patient so all these
theories that Sigman FY came up with and
other people came up with the most of
these theories lack empirical
evidence and that's why uh Psychiatry
psychology Etc psychology is still
something that's that's okay but
Psychiatry is is something that is
mostly Voodoo psychology is is a set set
of empirical behavioral uh patterns that
we
see which kind of makes sense
but Psychiatry is is voodoo not
psychology but
Psychiatry
um and and most of these theories that
people like Sigman came up with those
they have absolutely no empirical
evidence that validates
them uh so that's what I can say if you
are interested in Psychology then I I
I'm not sure I I am no Authority in the
field of psychology I suppose that there
will be institutions colleges
universities Etc where you could study
this Fe study psychology in
detail and uh I'm sure there are
applications in Psychology I'm sure it's
a reasonably lucrative field um Clinical
Psychology and behavioral psychology
that has applications everywhere in
industry in various uh domains in in in
uh in the military as well and so on so
there's a lot I think there's a lot of
scope for the field but psychiatry is is
just Voodoo it's nonsense and I'm sure
there are going to be comments from
certain
people which uh disagree which is fine
please feel free to
disagree uh Muhammad ismile says are the
Han Chinese colonizing and replacing the
local populations of East turkistan
Tibet and inner Mongolia how do you see
the future of the people of these
regions over the next 100 years okay so
let's take a look at the map and where's
the map one
second uh okay and let us
now uh remove that and we we are moving
towards uh the northeastern part beyond
the Indian Boundary so here we have
Tibet we have so-called sang they called
Tibet sh shiang or something you have
East turkistan Tibet and then obviously
you have Southern Mongolia which is
under Chinese
occupation uh about 50% of historical
Mongolia is currently under Chinese
occupation and like you say um
especially in places like Tibet uh the
the indigenous people are now a minority
which means that the Han Chinese have
colonized the place and these government
the Chinese government has settled so
many Han Chinese that the locals have
become a minority and I'm sure the same
uh issue exists in East turkistan which
is you know urum and all that turfan
those regions and you know Mongolia I'm
not sure about the extent of Han Chinese
immigration but but Tibet and Shang
definitely a lot so how do I see the
future for the people of these regions
if the
Chinese Empire it's an Empire okay the
Chinese Communist Party regime it's an
Empire if it stays in power the next 100
years then then Tibet will be Tibetan
culture will become something you will
find in
museums uh and uh it means that there is
no future for the ti language and Tian
culture and customs and all that it will
be allowed to exist as as a boutique
thing in some places like the same way
you have uh reservations for Indians or
or or American Indians or sorry Native
Americans in the United States and
Canada they're allowed to live in some
parts of the US they given some some
Third Rate land to live on and they live
a life of poverty and addiction and
whatnot there um that's how the
Americans that's how the United States
and Canada treat their natives the
Aboriginal true inhabitants uh the true
natives uh in the case of Tibet Etc you
will see Tibetan culture being allowed
to to exist
in as a tourist attraction as as a
curiosity but not something that's
widespread so they already U forcing
children in Tibet to study exclusively
in the Chinese language uh the Tibetan
language is not allowed that will in
just couple of generations destroy the
Tibetan language and the same happens in
India kids are forced to learn if they
want to have good jobs and good
prospects they they're forced to study
in English the same thing is happening
in India and we are doing it to
ourselves in Tibet the Chinese are doing
it to the Tibetans and similarly in sang
I think something similar is happening
so if China Remains the Same the next
100 years then these cultures will more
or less vanish and if they stay if they
continue to exist they'll continue exist
continue to exist as Curiosities and
Museum PC is nothing more than that so
it's it's going to be Bleak future if
that is going to be the
case
Okay
um run VI says what's the current
scenario of the Golden Triangle
especially it's China connection who
controlled it in the past and can the
West reclaim it what's India's role okay
good question let's go to the map once
again so when we're talking about the
Golden Triangle you can see the map here
we have India in the center now let's go
eastwards
the Golden Triangle is uh Burma
Laos
Cambodia Burma Laos mainly some parts of
Northern Thailand some Canada so sorry
Cambodia um marginally in there so the
Golden Triangle is this place this
geographical region where there is
lawlessness where there is little
government involvement
and it is run by mafias and Warlords and
the main um the main driver or of the
economy the main pillar of the economy
is
drugs um mainly poppy cultivation and
various other drugs uh drug drugs
essentially and this is a region that
supplies a significant amount of
significant percentage of the global uh
drug
usage um so in some places you just have
cultivation of poppies in some in some
places you also have factories that
actually transform the poppy the raw
product into the finished material which
is heroine or or whatever it is okay I'm
not very familiar with a lot of drugs
cocaine definitely doesn't come from
this because cocaine comes from the Coca
plant so we're talking about heroine and
various other drugs that are similar to
heroine opium heroine and whatnot okay
I'm not very familiar with what what
other drugs come out of this thing so
it's all based on puppies
poies what's the China connection uh
so how did the Golden
Triangle happen uh I'll not go into that
history but
which major Powers have been the driving
force behind this that's a good
question so we know about the Vietnam
War don't we something that happened
okay let's let's Google when did the
Vietnam War happened just to be very
clear about the dates and
not do it uh
haari Vietnam War so Vietnam War was
from 55 to 75 okay 20
years so the Vietnam war is why did it
happen it's because the Americans did
not want communism to take over in
Vietnam and of course they lost and
communism did take over in Vietnam and
that's a different
story now they also during the course of
the Vietnam War they also bombarded Laos
very big secret War happened in Laos
tremendous quantities of bombs were
dropped even today people in Laos on a
daily bases are getting maimed because
of unexploded
ordinance uh and you had another
disaster in
Cambodia now what the Americans did in
these regions is they would go to the
far off lands the mountains the hills
and all that and they would convert
people to
Christianity uh those people were called
the monards
mountain people in French liot so they
would go and convert these tribal people
people who are um isolated people who
live in the hills and mountains to
Christianity and they did the same in
Burma also lots of Christian converts of
recent converts in Burma Laos Vietnam
Etc and the at the same time the same
thing was happening in India's Far East
because of the great policies of the
great Mr neheru so nagaland mizoram
um
megala uh and other parts of the Far
East were converted almost entirely to
Christianity the local culture was wiped
out they tried the same in Manipur also
a lot of that is happening in arunachal
Pradesh so it's not just in India's
fares this entire region they've been
trying to do the same thing to control
the region
and the main produce is drugs so I think
the Americans have a significant role to
play have had historically a significant
role to play in The Golden Triangle the
Chinese obviously did not did not want
too much
American influence so they also had
their own pet Warlords and their pet
mafias who would operate in Northern
Myanmar in Laos Etc because these share
a border with China in Vietnam it was
not possible to that extent because
Vietnam was very strongly anti-china
actually weirdly after the 79 war and
all that so mainly Laos and Myanmar
Thailand is a very strongly Pro us
nation they have no choice so it was
mainly Laos in VI in Myanmar that this
uh these drug activities happened and
much of this was was exported to other
countries but now we know that it's also
happening in
Manipur um the the infiltrators who come
across from Burma the cookies they they
have been planting man poppy in Manipur
and all that so China is involved the US
has been involved in a very big way um
and yeah that's that's about that's
briefly about the Golden Triangle can
the West reclaim it what's India's role
India has no role in this India has
never played any extra extr territorial
geopolitical games even if they may be
to India's Advantage we have never done
that we have only allowed Outsiders to
mess up what's inside India so India has
no role in this uh can the West reclaim
it I'm sure the West is still involved
in some way or the other in the Golden
Triangle okay the just says I am a
student currently living in Germany can
you tell is it the right time to stay
here as war is looming what are the
European countries stand right now look
War isn't looming war is happening it's
the Ukraine war right um I don't see
this Ukraine war spilling over and
Crossing across into Poland Hungary and
eventually into Western Europe Germany
Etc I don't see that happening there is
a lot of Hysteria in the western media
that Putin wants to recreate the USSR
and he's going to March westwards is
going to
occupy Ukraine and then is going to the
next Target will be Poland then then
Herman Hungary and eventually uh Western
Europe that's the kind of Hysteria that
the Western media has
created I do not believe that at all uh
Russia had no option but to do what they
did in Ukraine because Ukraine was on
the verge of becoming a member of NATO
or a de facto member of NATO which means
that you would have US soldiers in
Ukraine you would have the US missiles
including nuclear missiles stationed
right at Russia's border so Russia could
not allow that to happen that's why this
war happened the special military
operation and you have you may have
noticed that they have not even run over
Ukraine even though they can they have
the military Firepower to flatten
Ukraine if they want and to end the war
in the next two three days if they want
but they have chosen not to do that they
have simply occupied the territories
that are Russian majority territories
and now it's a long War scenario and
eventually one hopes that a cease fire
will happen on whatever terms it happens
I think Trump will make it happen if
things go well and that should be it so
I do not foresee the war spilling over
westwards I don't see that at all Putin
is not a crazy person he's not a Madman
he's a very rational person he's a very
logical person person he's not a
warmonger he's just trying to secure
Russia's interests as every nation
should do do the same thing right so I
don't think I don't believe at all that
the war will spill over into the western
part of Europe unless the Americans do
something incredibly
provocative and even
then they won't make the Russians
retaliate by invading Western Europe if
they provoke the Russians too far it's
going to be nuclear war there's no other
thing that could happen and if there's
nuclear war it doesn't matter whether
you're sitting in Germany or
Madagascar okay maybe Madagascar is a
safe place actually sayfe safer
Place uh because if there's nuclear war
um the Russians and the Americans will
get
involved and that's the end of the world
essentially because the Americans have a
plan that if Russ if nuclear war happens
no country no major country should be
allowed to
survive which means they will also nuke
India in case of a nuclear conflict so I
would say that if you are fearful of War
then probably new New Zealand or M gasar
may be a good place to settle down
in okay so so my point is don't don't
worry too much about this I don't see
any such thing happening
hopefully uh okay let's take some more
questions from the
comments
lefo says can you see any scenario where
Russia loses the Ukraine war and the
West wins the only scenario in which I
see Russia losing the Ukraine war is
if is if there's a regime change in
Russia so either Mr Putin goes out of
power through whatever means or maybe he
dies these in these two hypothetical
scenarios the West wins and Russia
probably
loses unless there is an immediate
transition of leadership to an equally
strong leader who an equally capable
leader but if there's a regime change
and a
weak leadership comes to power then this
could happen otherwise I don't see any
scenario in which Russia loses the
Ukraine
war let's take one more question from
the comments debarun bachara says can
the aid or hakam Empire of Persia be
considered to be the first true Empire
of the world and why is the Roman Empire
considered to be the original greatest
Empire by the West I think the ainat
were much greater than the Romans
okay look um the AIDS were
not the
oldest uh Empire the first true Empire
the acced Empire see the first the
founder of the hakam Manish Empire the
Hamish Dynasty is hakam
Manish he is considered to be a semi-
mythical ruler we don't know if he
really existed and I don't know when did
he exist probably 1,000 BC roughly
roughly so if that is the case roughly
1,000 BC is when this guy lived the
founder of the Empire or the dynasty
then the acced Empire lasted from about
1,000 BC to about 330 BC it was
destroyed by Alexander the
Greek who defeated dasas II so that's
how long it lasted it was the first
great Persian Empire but that's not the
oldest Empire for example the Egyptian
Empire which we discussed some time ago
it was founded around 3,000 or 3,100
BC and it lasted until 332 BC once again
another Empire that was destroyed by
Alexander or or supplanted by Alexander
he put his minions in place as the as
the uh governors of Egypt and Alexander
became the de facto pharaoh of Egypt so
toy was the first governor of Egypt and
then he was the founder of the toic
dynasty so Egypt the Egyptian Empire
starts around 3,100 BC roughly then
there's another great Empire the TI
Empire present day Syria Anatolia that
was founded around 1600 16 or 1700 BC
and it lasted around until around 1200
or 1100 BC so that's before the cabinet
Empire and the HTI Empire was of Indo
Arian
origin their aristocracy was Indo Arian
they spoke Sanskrit and they woried Vic
gods and their neighbors the miani
Empire they were that Empire was founded
around 1600 BC and lasted until around
uh 1200 or so BC another Empire the
methanes whose aristocracy whose royalty
was of Indian origin and they also spoke
Sanskrit and then you have other Empires
like the Assyrian Empire 2000 BC to
until 600 BC or something and so on so
there are lots of Empires and and when
it comes to India we don't even know how
ancient India is we have records of
lineages of kings that go back godos how
many thousands of
years so when it comes to Indian history
a lot of it is is is crowded in mystery
and obscurity because of the burning of
our libraries and our records and the
destruction of our universities so we
don't even know how ancient our Empires
were U so definitely the aanish Empire
is not the oldest Empire or the first
true Empire there are many before it um
why is the Roman Empire considered to be
the greatest original Empire by the West
because the West is is is eurocentric
it's Western Centric they see everything
from there from the perspective of their
own
greatness so the Roman Empire was
nothing great compared to other Empires
that have existed
since or or previously but for them it
was the greatest of all so it's their
perspective look every everybody sees
himself or herself as the center of the
universe I mean that's human nature so
the
West sees the Roman EMP Empire is the
greatest I mean let them believe it it's
up to let them be
happy um yeah so that's how I see it
okay let's see some more questions from
the live chat one second let's remove
that yeah here we
are
okay deep Comm says can there be some
other artificial pandemic or disease of
disease X in the future look anything is
possible in the future there there have
been pandemics in the past there can be
there could be pandemics there probably
will be pandemics in the future
hopefully not in the next 100
years but it it's going to happen it's
it's it's a statistical certainty that
at some point time some point of time in
the future there'll be another pandemic
the last great pandemic before the
Corona virus was the the so called
Spanish Flu which actually originated in
China but it was called the Spanish Flu
which was around what
198 197 198 and it killed a tremendous
number of people worldwide including a
significant death toll in India so
you're going to have it in the future
will it be
artificial that could also be
possible that's also possible yeah
there's a lot of research that happens
uh worldwide in various labs in certain
countries virology
research why do whenever whenever
there's an ebola outbreak Ebola is a a
ghastly virus okay it has a 50 or 60%
mortality rate horrible mortality
rate uh so whenever there's an Ebola
outbreak someone in Africa why do teams
from the US China Etc visit these places
to offer assistance they're there to
collect samples of the virus okay and
then they research the virus and
probably they're doing stuff with it um
I'm
sure it's being weaponized in some form
or the other in some places and if that
somehow gets leaked or released either
deliberately or through accident into
the wild then we're going to have a
disaster on our hands so that's how an
AR artificial pandemic could happen but
but even if we disregard artificial
pandemics natural pandemics happen from
time to time we've had so many in the
past so it's it's more or less a
statistical certainty that at some point
of time in the future you will have some
other pandemic one hopes it's far in the
future and one hopes that we will have
sufficiently Advanced Medical Technology
that we can nip it in the
bird okay more questions um
what
else okay since you asking this question
so many times uh valti s says honest
review on latest Sony live show Freedom
at midnight I haven't watched it and I
have no interest in watching it I don't
watch these things man all these uh Ott
platforms with all their toes I don't
watch it don't have the time to watch it
and I look um it's not a topic that
interests me greatly um Gandhi nehu the
so-called Freedom at midnight which was
actually
uh which was dominan status not Freedom
so I don't know what it's about I'm not
going to watch it so I unfortunately
cannot give you my honest
review
okay panel says should do you think
India should join the BR the BR is is
not not doing well the belt and Road
initiative
uh the so-called what is it one
one one road to rule them all one belt
to bind them it's China's infrastructure
project across Eurasia it's it's it's
floundering the the Pakistan Corridor
the so-called China Pakistan economic
Corridor what what happened to it what
happened to the infrastructure is any
infastructure being built nothing is
happening and the CP U and and the Bri
what new construction is happening what
new development is happening nothing is
happening and this is the maritime silk
rout that that is also floundering after
the pandemic happened so the brri is
kind of dead in the water right now
there's not much activity happening many
nations have withdrawn from it it Italy
withdrew from the B very publicly last
year when Madame Jani was in Delhi for
the G20 Summit so the B is not doing
well why why should we join it we have
other things going on the i2u2 the and
various other projects that we are
working
on uh so yeah so I don't think India has
has any need to join the brri let's take
some more questions from the
comments okay bat Sharma says excuse me
what are your thoughts on being an
entrepreneur one have some level of
entrepreneurial quality or qualities as
an innate nature or can anyone be an
entrepreneur with specific learning and
guidance secondly how much does the
absence of Niche skills knowledge Etc
affect the entrepreneurial
Journey okay what are my thoughts on
being an entrepreneur so what is an
entrepreneur an entrepreneur is a person
an individual who creates a new business
and that person when he or she creates a
new business that person Bears all the
risks of creating a new business and if
successful if the business is successful
then the person will enjoy most of the
rewards most of the benefits in the
process of setting up a business such as
this is called
entrepreneurship so entrepreneurs are
essentially business people they create
new businesses
and they should play a key role in the
economy and what they do is they they uh
they solve problems every nation every
society has problem s so what you do as
an entrepreneur is you solve problems
you anticipate the needs of the people
and you bring new ideas to the market
and you bring new solutions to the
market that's what entrepreneurship is
so uh of course you need to have some
level of entrepreneurial capabilities or
or qualities some of it ideally should
be innate because look if you start a
new business it's a risky thing you're
going to have have to put up your own
money in many cases otherwise you to
take up take on big loans or mediumsized
loans from others which is again a risk
you're taking up a big risk and you're
it's like you're betting that yeah this
risk will pay off and I I'll get a big
reward at the end of this so you need to
have a good understanding of Economics
of finance of how to manage your
finances how to manage people how to
manage an organization and so and very
often what happens is that people who
have big
ideas as to how to solve problems they
are idea people they are creators but
they don't have the grounding in in
finance in in management and all that
and that's why lots of these businesses
fail so you need to have some level of
these qualities or you have to start
otherwise the other option is that you
start you start the business as a
partnership so you are the person who
has the idea and who knows how to create
the solution and and create the solution
and then your partner is going to be the
person who will manage the business and
manage the finances and manage the
people so you look after the technical
side of things and that person looks out
the other other side the the financial
side and the people side of things so
that is a solution that can work if you
do it as a solo person then you need to
have all the skills within yourself
otherwise there's a high chance you will
fail um so I would say that anybody who
is reasonably intelligent can become an
entrepreneur with but you to learn
things as you go ideally you should
learn some things you should have some
fundamentals understanding of the
fundamentals before you begin but a lot
of the stuff you're going to learn as
you as you as you go ahead as you create
as you as you
execute um and absence of Niche skills
how does that affect the entrepreneurial
entrepreneurial Journey you need the
skills that are pertinent or relevant to
the problem you're solving or or or
whatever new idea you're bringing into
the market if you don't have that skill
or those skills then how will you
execute how will you bring the new idea
to the market so that is is crucial
those Niche skills are crucial the
standard skills which is people
management and organizational management
and and financial man management you can
hire somebody to do that do that for you
or you can have someone as as a 505050
partner or whatever percentage partner
but those need skills that are pertinent
to the problem you're solving you need
to have those otherwise you simply can't
execute so there you have it let's take
one more question from the comments this
is by PR Paul
6361 uh making an extra $110,000 is
easier than trying to save $10,000 the
sooner you understand that the sooner
your life will improve and that's what
that's a quote from Elon Musk so how
valid is this does it depend on the or
does it depend on the context of an
individual and the individual's
surroundings uh that's an interesting
question so this is a question this is a
statement a quote from Elon Musk now
what perspective does this show us what
perspective does it reflect it reflects
an IT reflects entrepreneurial thinking
it reflects high growth thinking and
what he's trying to emphasize is the
power of generating new income rather
than focusing solely on cutting costs
let's say you have an
organization and instead of generating
new incomes and getting more customers
on board you're simply focusing on
cutting costs it's it's not going to do
really well right so uh and the same
applies to a person let's say you have a
salary of $10,000 a month let's say
which is actually a good salary even in
the
US um
now let's say uh you have two choices
you either cut down on your expenses and
save more money or you generate another
stream of income which is an extra
$10,000 what is better
I would say that generating more income
is always better than saving I'm not
saying saving should be disregarded you
should certainly not have any
unnecessary or frivolous expenditure you
should try and run you should try and
run a very tight ship you should uh
maximize your savings as far as possible
but on top of that if you have an extra
$10,000 stream of income how good is
that right so that makes sense but the
validity of this quote it depends on the
context okay it is is not universally
applicable it depends on your
circumstances the kind of opportunities
you have and the kind of mindset you
have so where does this kind of
statement hold true if you are living in
a developed economy which means that you
have access to resources you have access
to people with lot of skills you have
access to a lot of business
opportunities then you can create new
income streams easily if you are if you
have the ability to do that so if you
have if you are that sort of person then
it is not difficult for you to create
new in income streams and this will
definitely be more impactful than
focusing on being Frugal on cutting
costs so let's say you have a job but
you start a side hustle or you're
investing in skills that will lead you
to higher paying jobs or if or you can
Le or if you are leveraging assets that
can generate passive income then all of
that is is going to be much better than
simply cutting costs okay um now so so
that's so you need to be in that sort of
environment okay if you're in a poor
country if you are in a country that is
not a developed economy then how will
you be able to do that right so uh if
you have limited access to resources if
you're in a lowincome nation if you're
in an economically challenged
environment which is uh let's say it's a
western Nation but there's a recession
going on there then the opportunities to
earn your extra money extra stream of
income may not be readily available so
in that case the only viable strategy is
saving
money so that's the sort of thing so it
it all depends on the context and the of
the of the individual the circumstances
that you find yourself in and the
surroundings that you are within
sometimes even in Western nations in
high income Nations if there's a
recession if there's a bad government
you won't get all those opportunities
that you would otherwise get under
different circumstances so it all
depends on a lot of factors but as long
as you are in a good country with access
to
opportunities as long as that is true
then making extra money is way better
and easier than trying to save money and
and cut costs so for that I agree with
him okay what other questions do we have
on the live
chat okay daily dose of gaming says how
is Pakistan able to procure and develop
high-tech weapons and defense equipments
like drones like shaur 2 and JS like j35
despite having financial
crunch
look
Pakistan I I haven't said this for a
while right Pakistan is an artificial
temporary Nation Pakistan exists to
serve a certain geopolitical purpose in
the Indian subcontinent
region Pakistan was created by the
British to serve their geopolitical IC
interests in the Middle East as as well
as in the
subcontinent after the British seized to
be a firstr world power in 1956 or
thereabouts became a third rate world
power the Americans took over and they
became Pakistan's Big Daddy and for them
from the American perspective
India was an asset of the USSR so then
Pakistan had to become a US asset so so
Pakistan's the reason for its existence
is to counterbalance India and keep
India permanently Pally off balance in a
variety of ways and when the Americans
lost interest in Pakistan after the war
of after the war of on after the war on
terror after Osama was dead and all that
then the Chinese became Pakistan's Big
Daddy and the Chinese also had the same
objective of Pakistan the same use for
Pakistan to counterbalance India to keep
India off balance so the Chinese and the
Pak and the Americans Etc at various
points in time have supplied Pakistan
with various Technologies the Americans
gave them f-16s the Chinese are giving
them
g35s and whatever drones and what not so
the pakistanis
are they are getting this because they
serve a certain purpose they're not able
to develop these Technologies they will
claim that so and so technology was
jointly developed with other nations
that's just words the actual thing is
that they are being sold these
Technologies
um so that that's the deal now the
question is if if they have a financial
crunch how are they able to get this so
there are ways of laundering money and
and all that uh one doesn't need to go
into the details but the fact is that
look Pakistan has been defaulting on IMF
and other Lawns right uh IMF World bank
loans for such a long time but somehow
they still able to survive they're still
able to find the money to purchase
Essentials to to import food grains to
import petroleum despite having
defaulted multiple times on various
loans how is it how how are they able to
procure the money whatever way they able
to procure this money they're also able
to procure the money to buy the this
equipment that's just the way it
works so there we have it
um
uh Karan Alat says what's your favorite
branch in Mathematics Algebra analysis
topology geometry number Theory or any
other I think analysis number Theory
very interesting topics I have a couple
of books somewhere here
by teren
stal
um very good books uh number the is good
anal I think all branches of mathematics
are beautiful geometry is a beautiful
thing topology I haven't really delved
too much into that algebra everyone does
it um yeah I would say number Theory and
Analysis I would say
that all right uh
Krishna goind Alfred ragunath bulay says
do you think that do you think the
language used in the IVC stamps Indus
Valley Civilization era stamps could be
Pachi aaba with respect to the
traditional timeline chronology I I'm
not sure um the latest uh research done
by a gentleman called yajan
who seems to have deciphered the uh the
sarasti synu era script according to
this
research he's able to read what's
written on each of these seals and it's
actually Sanskrit so it is not an upper
brancha language it is sanskrit
itself uh now obviously that research
will have to be peer reviewed there are
very few few people who can do it
because he has used cryptographic crypto
cryptological techniques cryptographic
techniques to decipher the the scrypt by
treating it as a cryptogram so very few
people have the competence to peer
review that sort of research so it's
going to take some time but assuming it
is correct the assuming this research is
correct then the language in these SEALS
or stamps is sanskrit itself not an
upper brunal language I think the upper
brunal language is uh they evolved out
of Sanskrit around 1,000 BC or something
around that time because when it comes
to magad in the Moria period Etc we had
upper Bunch languages like like Pali Etc
which are derivatives of
Sanskrit so I think the process of upper
Branch upper Branch upper
branz
started around 1,000 BC or maybe even
before that but when we're talking about
the IVC seals we're talking about 3,000
4,000 BC or around 2,500 BC so the
language in those seals seems to be
Sanskrit okay some questions I'm seeing
that I have already answered before
kardashi scale Dyson
spars um all
that what else do we have okay let me
take one more question from uh the
the the comments let's take a question
about physics for a for a change because
I haven't done physics for a very long
time so harj baa says can you please
explain the holographic principle of
black holes in
space the holographic principle
um
okay
so it applies to black holes it also
applies to the universe so think of a
balloon you take a balloon you fill air
into it in it and it expands and you
have a balloon of a certain size okay so
inside your balloon there is a space
that space is filled with
air now here's the the central idea of
the holographic principle I'm using an
analogy of a balloon so everything
inside the balloon all of that stuff can
be described just using the outside
surface of the
balloon essentially it's like all the
information about what is inside the
balloon and all the instructions about
what's happening inside the balloon are
written on the surface of the
balloon that's an analogy now let's talk
about black holes so black holes as we
know are these objects that uh um
that are are dark and they have an event
horizon Beyond which anything if
anything enters there it will never come
out even light okay they don't let even
anything es Escape even light so now
there's something really strange about
black holes the amount of stuff matter
inside a black hole depends on the
surface area of the black hole the
outside
layer so it doesn't depend on how big
the black hole is inside how much volume
is inside all the information about
what's inside the black hole is encoded
on the surface of the black hole so
that's the holographic principle you
know what a hologram is is Right a
hologram is a flat picture that appears
to be three-dimensional depending on how
you look at it so the same thing applies
to black holes the holographic principle
that uh the surface encodes everything
the the entirety of the information of
what's about what's happening
inside and the same thing May apply to
the universe itself which means that
there is an there could be a a layer
outside the universe okay uh that that
uh encodes all information about
everything that's uh that's happening
inside the universe so there essentially
could be an invisible or or visible
surface outside the universe that
encloses the Universe and on the surface
is encoded information about everything
that's inside the universe so that is
the holographic
principle
now
um anupam jwal says latest scientific
Studies have shown that black holes
aren't just absorbers but they have been
they've also been seen emitting matter
and energy this is called Hawking
radiation uh so when Stephen Hawking uh
visited Russia in the 1950s or 60s he
met a two scientists called novikov and
zeldovich
novikov for sure and novikov showed
Hawking that if you use if you apply the
laws of thermodynamics to black holes
and black holes have a temperature and
we know that any object that has a
temperature emits heat and what is heat
it's
radiation so Hawking then came come came
back to the UK and he derived the semi
semi classical semi- Quantum solution to
this problem and he demonstrated
mathematically that black holes have
temperature and they emit
radiation they emit radiation and
radiation in the form of the radiation
that they emit have a black it has a
black body Spectrum it's entirely random
completely random genuine
Randomness uh and black holes have
temperature so large black holes are
cooled small black holes are hot the
larger of black hole the colder it is
the smaller black hole the hotter it is
the smaller black hole the faster it
radiates so it can radiate photons it
can
radiate protons antiprotons any kind of
stuff matter and energy like you saying
but black holes have never been observed
emitting matter energy that is not
correct we have never observed Hawking
radiation never
ever uh scientists in the at The
whitesman Institute in Israel they did
an an experiment with a with with an
acoustic black hole so it's it's uh
something that similar to a black hole
it's like U the the kind of kind of like
the vortex in a sink and so they
demonstrated that Hawking radiation can
be a similar phenomenon can have can can
be observed in that but that's an
acoustic analogy for black hole it's not
an actual black hole so this is not a
light latest scientific study it's
something that happened in the 1960s
Stephen Hawking is the originator that's
why it's called Hawking radiation so
yeah we know Hawking radiation
theoretically exists but we we don't
have any black hole in a lab that we can
observe if we had a black hole in a lab
then we would be able to observe hacking
radiation but we don't have it so we
have never observed this but
theoretically it should hold true that's
what we
know all right
um okay this is a question I took up but
I'll take it again akiles says what can
you tell us about the Russian missile to
Ukraine last week and are they leading
to World War II so this is a repeated
question so that's the problem with with
live chat lots of questions are repeated
which is why I'm taking questions from
the comments as well so the Russian
missile that the Russians launched on
Ukraine was an intermediate rage
ballistic missile not an ICBM like lots
of news outlets have been claiming and
it may or may not have been uh equipped
with mirv Warheads but non-nuclear
warheads and is it leading to World War
II hopefully not the Americans seem to
be trying to provoke the Russians into
starting World War I so that they can
blame Russia but Putin is not crazy he's
a very sane man so I don't think World
War I 3 will happen but we are
dangerously closer to World War II than
we were two weeks ago
yeah
uh Mahari vashishta says how to reduce
air pollution in Delhi
NCR tremendous problem in
DHI um last week I saw at one point in
time the air quality aqi in Delhi was
about 1,500 or something it's the
equivalent of smoking I don't know 50
cigarettes in one day imagine smoking 50
cigarettes in one day a regular person
will go to hospital but in Delhi
everybody is smoking that including
little kids including new newborn babies
it is healthier to smoke a
cigarette in
Bangalore than to do yoga in
Delhi that's how bad the pollution is
getting and is it because of
Diwali is it because of firecrackers
what nonsense it's because of stubble
burning in Punjab possibly harana I'm
not sure but Punjab for sure so what's
the solution you have to prevent Farmers
from burning stubble burning stubble is
the easiest thing in the world because
you don't have to cut it and dis and and
dispose of it just burn it off right it
also fertilizes the soil but it
unleashes this incredible
torrent of pollution air pollution that
ches the national Capital so what's the
solution one solution is for the
government to give Farmers a certain
amount of money for the stubble and then
you can recycle the stubble or or do
something with it create bricks that you
can pave buildings with or or use in
building roads or something there are
lots of solutions you can convert it
into into ethanol or whatever but that
would involve the government either
harshly prohibiting the farmers Farmers
from burning stubble or offering them
financial compensation for every ton of
of stubble that they cut and give to the
government but in that case they will
start raising prices the farmers right
naturally when there's a chance to make
money they'll want to make more money so
I don't know whatever the solution is
the government needs to find it and they
need to prevent Farmers from burning
stubble I'm sure this can be enforced
easily I'm sure there'll be Farmers
protest in that case again but so be it
I
mean the health of people is more
important than these things right so I'm
sure there are lots of ways of doing it
one way is to for the government to give
financial compensation to the farmers
for every ton of stubble they give to
the government and then you recycle it
turn it into ethanol turn into bricks or
whatever that's one possible solution
I'm sure there are other Creative
Solutions that do
exist okay let's take a couple more
questions and then we'll be done
so
uh what else do we
have um
let's see something
uh okay mlan says why do Buddhists
follow an additional religion how don't
know much countries that only follow
Buddhism what additional religion do
Buddhists
follow uh okay if you look at
Thailand uh if you go to Bangkok for
instance every street almost every
street corner has a statue of Vishnu of
Lord Vishnu bhagan Vishnu is bhagan
Vishnu a Buddhist God god well Buddha is
apparently an avatar of Vishnu so yeah
but Vishnu is also a Hindu god I mean
Vishnu predates
Buddhism predates shakam Buddha it's at
least and if you go to Thailand you will
see people worshiping Shiva you will see
worshiping people worshiping Lord Shiva
Lord Ganesh a variety of Hindu gods and
goddesses if you go to Japan you will
find people worshipping all kinds of
Hindu gods and goddesses with Japanese
names and they are apparently Buddhist
Gods ben zen is sarasti
uh Kangen is Lord Ganesh and so on lots
and there is Lord Shiva as well there is
bav and whatnot but with Japanese names
um and so on so um it's not about
following an additional religion I you
know lots of people disagree with me and
they can keep on disagreeing but I don't
see any difference between Buddhism and
Hinduism it's all part of the dhic
collective there are so many different
dhic paths puns so is is is V ofm now a
separate religion and is Chism also a
separate religion they have very
different rituals and traditions so are
we going to make everything a separate
religion similarly Buddhism is also not
a separate religion it's just one of the
dharmic paths but foreigners have put
this into our minds in our textbooks and
our prophetes keep on doing it that
Buddhism is a separate religion and if
Buddhists also worship the the the
various Hindu gods and they are
following two religions what utter
nonsense it's the same tradition it's
the same path so I don't agree that
budhist follow additional religions and
in in the east in Asia there's a lot of
syncretization for example in Japan you
have you have a syncratic belief system
which combines Shinto and Buddhism and
Hinduism and in lots of different parts
of Asia and India also there are lots of
local
beliefs that have been absorbed into the
overall larger belief system so there's
a lot of syncretism lots of animism
animistic practices and so on that that
get uh synchronized with Hinduism
Buddhism whatever so that's just the way
it is it's it's because it's a very
Democratic civilization everything is
allowed nothing is not allowed that's
how it is okay I think uh we have
crossed Way Beyond two hours so with
that I'm going to end today's session
thank you very much everybody for the
questions I know there are lots of
questions that I could not answer but
that's why we have the future episodes
and I'll keep on taking your questions
over there so thank you so much
everybody have a good day have a good
night keep asking questions all the time
keep learning and keep raising your
standards I will see you in next week's
live stream Take Care thank you see you